# Joshua Powers

**Data Scientist** 

**Objective**: A senior, hands-on position in data analytics/science at an organization whose mission inspires me.

11005 Ring Rd, Reston, VA 20190 jpowersbaseball@gmail.com / (703) 725 4173

### **Profile**

I develop solutions to difficult problems with insightful approaches, mature teamwork and good taste. The technical substance of my career has been in applied Artificial Intelligence, Natural Language Processing and Formal Knowledge Representation. I have regularly collaborated with and managed every skill level from PhDs to interns. My work has been funded by government research programs and has been awarded patents.

## **Skills**

### **Artificial Intelligence**

Deep Learning Random Forests Formal Reasoning

#### **Platforms**

Amazon Sagemaker Google Natural Language OpenNLP

### **Natural Language Processing**

Text Classification Entity Extraction Machine Translation

### Languages

Python Java RDF/OWL

# Work Experience

### WorldAware, Reston, VA

VP, Data Analytics

2017-Present

Led high-performing team on a variety of data science projects to accelerate the company's ability to exploit both raw and authored intelligence. Specific technologies include machine translation, auto-classification of unstructured text, large-scale geospatial clustering and analysis.

## LemonFish Technologies, Reston, VA

CTO 2015-2017

Led development of data breach detection platform used for both intellectual property and PII breaches. Designed and built automated query generation from unstructured text. Built Dark Web data collection and analysis components involving The Onion Router (TOR) network, anonymization proxies, IRC collection and query salting. Built breach investigation tools for personal, corporate and ad-hoc scopes.

### Securboration, Melbourne, FL (remote)

CTO 2010-2015

Responsible for developing and managing the evolution of diverse technology portfolio. Principal Investigator on multiple SBIR Phase I, II and III efforts, representing more than \$6 million of funding from DARPA, AFRL and FAA. Developed novel information extraction, clustering and semantic search technologies across a wide variety of use cases. Received patent 9256669, "Stochastic document clustering using rare features."

### CLR, Arlington, VA

Metadata Architect 2007-2010

Led Joint DoD/Intelligence Community working group for Automated Metadata Population Service (AMPS), a semantic web-enabled software service that produces discovery metadata for documents, datasets and web service assets. Built the semantic and linguistic logic to support automated keyword and category extraction. Provided technical guidance to contractors working on the follow-on productization effort for AMPS and started the software.forge.mil project to host AMPS code and developer guidance.

## **Education**

## **Stanford University**

BS, Artificial Intelligence

1994